[chatter]
>> Paulo: Ok, hello.
>> Patrick: Can you all hear it?
>> Paulo: So I guess I'll speak really close.
So, hello everyone.
Before I start, really quickly, we're recording
this on that camera over there, but it only
records in thirty-minute intervals, so I have
a timer and if I can ask - when it goes off
- someone just to re-click the button so that
we can record it.
Or I guess Patrick can do it as well.
Alright, so I'm talking about motion detection
in JavaScript... in the browser.
Not this type of motion in the window but
in a video so that would be a webcam stream
or a video file.
Alright, let's get into it.
So just a little about myself:
I was born in Brazil, but I grew up in California.
I studied in Bilbao and then that prompted
me to move to Barcelona, and I've been here
for a little over five years.
I'm an Information Architect at a company
here called Waytostay (we do apartment rentals).
I've been doing JavaScript development for
about 10 years - more seriously in the past
four or five.
So I wanted to mention this: that I am not
an expert in video or motion graphics.
And I mention that not to undermine me, but
to encourage you guys because this is about
video and graphics and don't get intimidated
if you don't know something.
I got into this with this project that I did.
We're also dealing the the canvas and I've
never done too much work with the canvas - just
to accompany the previous comment.
Alright so, what I'm going to be talking about:
The reason I put "Questions" first is because
I like an interactive audience so if you guys
have question or comments feel free to shout
them out. Don't be rude, but just raise your
hands or ask away and we'll interact like
that.
And that helps me know too if you guys are
following along or if I'm boring you guys
so don't be afraid.
Ok, so first thing - I'll just do an overview.
This project that I did is a pretty small
project but it was something I wanted to challenge
myself with to see if it was possible.
Essentially it was to detect movement in a
video as I've said.
So there's going to be three... I'll go through
3 different steps that I did to get to that
stage.
And then finally to... the difference between
detecting movement, by the way... I separated
it out into "Detect Movement" (which is just
random motion) and then "Detecting Motion"
is detecting the direction of the motion.
And then if we have time we'll just talk about
some potential applications that this can
be used for.
And feel free to think - if you think of anything
during the presentation, I'll ask if you guys
have any additional suggestions.
Ok, so on to "The Challenge."
This is what I wanted to do: to perform real-time
image stabilization in the browser.
A quick foreshadow: I did not get to this.
It's actually pretty difficult, and we'll
talk about why.
But that's what I set out to do.
So, in order to be able to stabilize an image,
you need to counteract the motion that's happening
in the video.
If that's not intuitive it will become so.
So in order to do that, you need to determine
the direction of the motion.
But first you have to be able to detect if
there is movement in the video.
So I'm actually going to go through these
three points but in reverse order cause I
actually started with number 3 since it's
the easiest.
Uhh, for the sake of time, let's just ignore
that little asterix.
Ok, I wanted to show this.
So this was the hope - this would be like
the goal, the ultimate goal to be able to
do.
So this is in Adobe After Effects - which
is a video editing program (quite sophisticated)
and the way you can do image stabilization
in here is you actually find a point that
you want to track in your video, you track
it (not in real-time),
and what it does is it basically plots the
points where that pixel or the area you defined,
where it moved to.
With that information, then when you actually
compile the movie or process it,
you can counteract the motion.
So it would look something like this.
So if that screen wasn't moving around, the
image in the video would be moving around
and that's what we want to prevent.
So that's what I had in my head; that's what
I was trying to do in JavaScript,
um, so let's see where I got.
Alright, the first thing we have to do is...
with the video element, we don't have access
to the pixel data, we don't have access to
the frames.
We have access to be able to pause, play,
slow down, volume, things like that.
So to get started, we have to put all the
image data into the canvas cause that will
allow us to manipulate and read the pixels.
So the first step is to transfer the video
to the canvas.
Now this actually isn't too hard and there's
a small code snippet here.
You guys definitely won't be able to read
that.
Um, essentially we have a source video which
is just the DOM element,
we set up a canvas,
setup the proper width and height to just
be the same as the video
and here's just a small function (it's a loop
function that calls itself) and all we're
doing...
I know this is really difficult, let me zoom
in.
Alright, still pretty light but um - there's
this function which is part of the context
object which I'll talk a little bit about
later - and all your doing is specifying the
actual DOM element (which is just "document.getElementById");
you just pass that, the starting coordinates
(so top left in x y), and then how much of
the image you
want to draw
[indistinct]
And if you loop this, everytime you call it,
it will draw the frame onto your canvas.
And you might think this would generate a
big overhead, but it's actually pretty performant
so there's no problem there.
This is calling itself at 40 frames per second.
The reason for that is because I'm using my
webcam which has a slower framerate than most
videos.
Typically we'd want 60fps.
In this case, actually, sometimes I needed
to lower it a little bit to 30 or even 20.
No questions?
Alright. So, hopefully the webcam will work
ok... so...
You guys can see me? Over there, not here.
This is the video element - you can see I
have the controls.
I can pause it play again. That's the standard
video element.
And then what I have over there on the right
is a canvas which is being drawn every,
40 times a second. And you can see no problems
with lag.
Alright...
>> Audience: I have a question. Are you dropping
frames or not to maintain the frame rate?
>> Paulo: Dropping frames?
>> Audience: Yeah.
>> Paulo: I might be.
So what's happening in that function that's
calling itself, is it's calling itself 40
times a second. If that video is playing faster
that that, I'm only capturing the frame rate
that I'm repeating at.
So I can bump that up, and actually people
would recommend - people like Paul Irish who
is a big advocate of it (at least the first
time I heard of it anyway) - of using the...
I drew a blank right now... the request...
request frame rate... requestAnimationFrame,
yeah that's it.
And what that does is the browser determines
how many times to call it, and it optimizes
it for you. So it will give you the best that
you can get basically.
The reason I'm not using that is because since
the webcam is definitely slower than 60fps,
you get a flash effect going on because as
you're trying to draw faster than the video
is giving you,
you get every once in a while a black frame
because there's nothing to draw,
so I did it manually calling a setTimeout.
Does that answer the...? Good?
>> Audience: Thank you.
>> Paulo: Ok, so let's get in to a little
bit...
talking about the canvas element and how it
does it's thing.
So that thing I mentioned earlier (the context)
that's actually how you interact with the
canvas.
This you can assume to be the actual canvas
element in the DOM (document.getElementById),
and you have to "getContext" of the canvas
which is what we'll be working with.
It's kind of out of scope so we don't need
to talk about it too much.
So once you have this context you can do interesting
things with the data that's in them.
We're going to be using these two functions
- they were the only ones of the context that
I use in this project.
Which is "getImageData" - which does the following:
So over here you can't see it well, but there
is a square which is the whole canvas frame.
And you can basically say: "give me all the
data that starts at this coordinate (x and
y) for this width and height.
So that's that box.
It's kind of self-explanatory, no? With the
image?
So what this will do is return an object that
has data of the image in this area.
So that's how you get it from an existing
canvas.
But you can also create one (with blank data)
so that you can use it without having to draw
it in the browser (which we actually do).
Any questions about that? This is probably
the most complex or technical part of this
so...
[laughter]
Ok, so this "imageData" is the object I was
talking about that is returned by that call.
What it does - let me advance one more - so
it actually returns an "imageData" object
which has a property in it call "data" which
is what we are actually going to use.
So what this does (the .data) is an array
containing all the pixel data for your imageData.
It's a little bit counterintuitive and you
can't see because I made it black here but
that's an "a".
So essentially it returns an array that for
every pixel, it has four items in the array.
They're sequential and they represent the
sub-pixels of a pixel (all the different channels):
red, green, blue and the alpha channel for
every pixel.
So that's pretty cool.
So now we have... we can manipulate down to
the pixel level of our image.
So all sorts of possibilities open up.
So just in this example (this visual example
I have setup) this is a 4 by 3 grid
We got one, two, three, four going across
and three down,
so the length of the array is 48 cause we
had to multple by four because of the differnt
sub channels.
Alright, more code.
Alright, I'll try to talk through it cause
I think it's going to be hard to see.
Sooo, this is the same frameLoop function
that we had before (that tiny one that was
down here) I've just added some things.
We create a blank image data
out of a source context with the same width
and height as our video frame.
And we store that here temporarily. We're
gonna store something in there that will be
usable to visualize things later.
Now, to be able to detect movement, you need
to be able to compare at least two frames,
right?
If you take a picture on a [still] camera,
there's no real movement there so you need
at least two frames.
So over here we're going to be comparing the
previous (from the previous iteration) and
the current one.
So this if statement is only used for the
first iteration where we don't have a previous
frame.
Then we have this special function here which
is on the next slide
where we pass in this blank image data object
and then the current and previous frames.
Now let's go see what is happening there.
And that other stuff is just to repeat the
loop.
Ok so this is the "compareFrames" function.
So I'm passing in the imageData object of
the current and previous frame.
I do ".data" on them so that we get the actual
array that I want to check
and I start my loop.
So I have a loop that's looping through every
single pixel in my imageData frame.
Now if you remember, this is going to iterate
through every single sub-pixel
which we don't actually need to do,
so my increment down at the bottom does a
"plus four"
so then I can advance to the next actual pixel
instead of sub-pixel.
So inside this loop,
there's a function here called "luma" which
is calculating the lumniosity of the pixel.
So, this is also going to start getting ahead
of us, but:
when you have a color image as we have an
rgb channel,
if you want to convert it to black and white
all you care about is the brightness of each
sub-pixel.
So "is there a lot of red?" if there's "few
green" or "a lot of blue."
So the way you calculate the lumninosity of
it is you average the three pixels.
So here I'm passing in the "r" (which is the
red channel) then the next one (so plus 1)
which would be the green and then the blue.
So now down here is the luma function (I know
you can't see it) all it's doing is adding
"r + g + b" and dividing by three.
And by the way, "rgb" has a value between
0 and 255 just like when you set a color in
CSS - it can have that range.
Alright, so this is going to return... so
now...
this represents the gray scale value of the
pixel that we're currently on - for the current
and previous frame.
And now I do a difference between them - subtract
each other, absolute value - so now I have
how much brightness changed on the current
pixel that I have.
You can start seeing how we're getting to
detecting if there is a difference between
a previous and a current frame that are stacked
on top of each other.
Yeah?
Ok, umm...
this is kind of an interesting part as well:
I set a "threshold"
(which I think I did up on top)
threshold set to 20 (so that's in the value
range: 0-255)...
so you can play with this and it will basically
be the threshold of whether the brightness
difference was big enough to actually consider
movement.
And we'll actually be able to play with that
in another example.
So in...
what this allows you to do is if it's above
the threshold set the pixel to white because
then it's easier to see if you're trying to
visualize it.
If not, set it to black.
And then we do a count if this happens because
we want to know how many of these "diffPixels"
(as I call it)
how many of these "diffPixels" happened throughout
the frame.
Ok, and then I write this value (255 or 0)
out to my reference imageData object that
I craeated earlier and passed into the function.
I basically write "full value" (255) to all
the channels (r, g, and b) and that will produce
white.
Alright, thanks for going through that. I
know it's really dark and
you probably didn't see as much as you should
have.
Ok so now we're going to detect movement.
So what's going on here?
I have the video element as before.
But my canvas element, as you can see,
it's not drawing the image,
it's drawing the difference of the pixels
data.
So that little blue bar that's moving there,
all that's showing... is representing the
number of white pixels that you see on that
canvas. K?
So that loop that I was doing is basically
going through every single pixel, every frame
(and this is 40 times a seconds times all
the pixels in the image).
So yes, my fan does start going after a while.
But, that's pretty neat.
So if I stand totally still, it goes black.
And if I start moving, you can see the difference.
If I move real fast, the blue bar jumps up.
Pretty nice.
And then this slider that I setup is bound
to the threshold value.
So if I turn it down it becomes less sensative.
See I'm moving? There are fewer white pixels.
If I bump it up all the way, it whites out
because there's always "less than or equal
to 0" difference between the pixels.
So, there - I'm keeping it pretty high
and we can see the actual noise from the image
because it's a shitty camera
[laughter]
and because we're in a basement so there's
not a lot of light.
Ok, now this checkbox,
what this does is it enables or disables that
condition where I had to force it to be white
or black.
If I turn that off...
let me turn the sensitivity up a bit...
actually that won't make too much of a difference.
So now you see something different. Now you're
actually seeing the...
I just got my reminder to... ah, you did?
Terrific, thanks. I'll start it again...
Ok so, I turned off the "binary diff" so now
we're actually seeing the luminosity difference
of the pixels.
Just kind of fun.
The other is much more useful because we just
care about how many of those pixels we consider
to be a "motion pixel".
Alright, that's it for that demo.
Good so far still?
You can hear me ok?
How are we doing on time?
Ok, I'm going to skip this section.
What I was going to do is, in Photoshop, you
can setup different layers and it's a good
way to be able to visualize and interact with
what's happening in the code we just setup.
Photoshop let's you setup different layers
and
it allows you to blend those in several different
ways.
And one of them is called "Difference"
and what it does is essentially the exact
same thing:
it does a difference between the pixels and
if there is a difference,
it will show it in white and if not in black.
So I'll skip that because I think you guys
got that.
Ok, let's get into this because this is the
final part.
So now to be able to detect the actual direction
of the motion.
So we've been able to detect movement,
does anyone have any ideas of how we might
detect the direction of the movement?
Maybe.
Ok, I'll give you five seconds...
Well, let's walk through it.
So this is my solution, there might be others,
but this is the simplest I could think of.
First we get the number of pixels (like we
were doing with that blue bar)
So the number of [white] pixels in the current
difference frame.
So now we have a number value.
What I decided to do is,
imagine I have two layers,
this is the current and this is the previous.
So in the same iteration loop,
before I move on to the next,
I shift the prvious frame a little bit - I
did it by three pixels.
So now with the shift,
I get the number of pixels again
(do the same diff I did before)
and if there are fewer pixels from the previous
one
I know the direction of the movement happened
in the same way that I moved my difference
frame.
This is actually where the Photoshop example
might of come in handy.
Are there any doubts about that?
It's a little hard to visualize without a
reference.
Ok. And else, the movement happened in the
other direction.
I mean, that's really simplistic, but we're
we're also not going for a high level of detection.
And then you can repeat that for the other
axis (the y axis)
to be able to detection motion up and down
cause this will only detect it on one axis
(the x axis).
Ok let's get a demo and if there are any doubts,
this should clear them up.
Ok, so we basically have the same setup here,
the video on the left,
but the difference that we're seeing now in
the canvas (in black and white)...
you'll notice that if I stand still,
there's still a diffrence
and the reason is because what I'm showing
here in this canvas is the comparison of the
shifted previous frame.
So all the white that's showing there is 3
pixels to the left
(or right, I forgot which one it is)
of the difference.
So now the blue bar is still showing the same
data.
So if I stand still it shows how many white
pixels are in there.
But if I move, let's see,
if I move this way
you still have white pixels.
You can see the blue bar moving to the right
because I'm basically increasing the number
of pixels on the thing.
But if I move it in the other direction, you'll
notice my hand kind of goes black.
And that's because I'm catching up to the
shift that I did with the previous frame.
And it actually works, if you look at the
blue bar and I move my body, you'll notice
it goes down.
And if I move over to the right, it goes up.
So right there, I've detected direction on
one of the axis.
So that's pretty... not too bad.
And I did it all on my own!
[laughter]
And I think we're out of time, so...
maybe we'll skip this part.
Just some potential applications that we can
use this for.
I guess we'll count this as part of the "Questions"
segment at the end.
So anyone with any possible suggestions?
I'll go over my list and maybe that will give
you ideas.
That one doesn't actually apply to motion
so I'll skip it.
It's just other things that you can do with
the pixel data on the canvas.
I should show this because it is a nice game
that someone setup
using the exact same concept...
which is pretty neat.
So what this guy did,
is he setup a similar thing (you can see on
the bottom right there it's showing the difference
pixels).
But what he does is up here where there are
symbols,
he has basically a square around each one
and he's seeing how many white pixels is in
this area.
So that allows you to detect movement in a
certain position of the video.
So what he did is he attached a sounds to
each note so you can play...
It's kind of fun.
I mean he's doing just that: how many white
pixels are in that area, he also has a threshold
and that's it.
[laughter]
That's not too bad.
So there's a game application.
And then of course you, you know, can get
creative.
You can imagine a website that's high on accesibility
for people that have trouble using the mouse
or a keyboard
and if you need to interact with simple motion
(left or right, up or down) you could, in
theory,
use the same technique and you can wave...
I mean, you can imagine on this presentation
to scroll between slides
you can just do that and it should be able
to know to slide left or right.
That, does it. Thank you very much!
This project that I started, I called it "Shaky
Shake JS".
I'm still going to attempt to do some type
of simple image stabilization.
It should be possible in theory with the example
I was showing you.
Obviously it depends on a lot of things:
on what background you have,
how much movement you have aside from yourself,
but it should be possible.
There's my info. I'm not very active on Twitter
(I'm getting there), but I have been on Google
plus. Thank you.
[applause]
>> Patrick: Any questions?
>> Audience: The pictures you are taking with
the camera, are still images? Or actual motion...
>> Paulo: That camera or this camera?
Oh, well, it's a video.
>> Audience: What type of compression are
you using? Still image compression (jpeg)
or a motion jpeg, or H.264?
>> Paulo: Ok so I'll just repeat the question
for those who didn't hear and for the video.
He's asking what type of compression, if any,
that the video is doing that we're reading
- is that good more or less?
I'm not doing anything actually with the video.
Whatever image comes from the video DOM element,
I'm painting that on to my canvas.
>> Audience: So you're just capturing still
images?
>> Paulo: Yeah, yeah exactly. Yes effectively,
correct. So every...
40 times a second, it's grabbing whatever
is on the video image just as if I did a screenshot
essentially and it's painting that.
So if your video has a high...
ideally, you would want to match the same
frame rate that the video is playing at.
I don't know the exact frame rate of my camera,
but ideally in this example it would match
the exact thing.
You might have noticed that in those black
and white images on the canvas there was a
little bit of a blink?
And that's because I'm actually capturing
faster than the camera is spitting out.
So every once in a while it tries to grab
an image that...
it turns black because it's the exact same
that I already have from before.
Because it's going faster.
Ok.
>> Audience: How do you grab the video...
the live video from the camera?
>> Paulo: Ok that was... well I'm already
disconnected, but in the beginning umm...
I showed an example... the first code snippet
which was a very small one,
in that loop that I have, the context (the
canvas context)
has a function called which is called "drawImage"
- I think that's what it is -
and you can pass in the video DOM element,
and it does it for you.
So it grabs whatever is in the video element
and paints it on to your canvas.
So there's actually no work there that I did.
>> Audience: I ask because I worked with the
video tag, like 2 years ago and I think it
was probably under development back then or
maybe I didn't research very well, and you
couldn't load live video to the video tag.
Basically you could only load the [indistinct]
video.
>> Paulo: Ah, actually this is still under,
or it's not a standard yet.
Well, it's already disconnect, but there's
a "getMedia" ...
"getWeb..."
I forget what it is.
There's a function where you can do "win...
navigator.getMediaElement" and that grabs
your webcam.
So here I'm actually using "webkitGetMedia..."
because all the browsers have their vendor-specific
ones.
So yeah, it's still under... it's not standard
yet, so [indistinct]
That example with the game, he... when he
did that, he had to use Chrome Canary
because it was only available on that build.
But right now it's in the distributed version.
I should probably stop now because I'm way
over.
[applause]